Doble, William J. Papers 5182
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William J. Doble Papers
1921-1971
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Doble, William J.
5182
16 cubic feet
16 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
Files of the chairman of the New York Central Railroad (Lines West) of the Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen of America, including information regarding labor relations on the Michigan Central, Peoria and Eastern, and Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroads.
3834064
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 30, 1974
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 01, 2016
Biographical / Historical
William Doble was born October 25, 1904, in Exetes, Devon, England. He immigrated to the U.S. and found employment in the railroad industry. Doble was a member of the Blue Mason Lodge and the OPA Advisory Committee.
Doble joined the Brotherhood of Railroad Signalman of America in 1924. With only an elementary school education he rose through the ranks to the position of chief signalman and ultimately became General Chairman of the Brotherhood, for New York Central, Lines West. His jurisdiction extended to local unions of the Big Four, the Michigan Central Railroad, the New York Central Railroad, the Peoria and Eastern Railway, and, Foreman and Inspector of the Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad. He served in the office of General Chairman from 1931 to 1962 (as far as could be discerned from the collection). From his desk in Ferndale, Michigan, he handled grievances and channeled labor-management relations. Doble functioned as the coordinator of subordinate locals' activities, grievance claims, and disputes concerning conditions of employment.
Biographical / Historical
The railroad signal department performs the vital functions of expediting and controlling traffic while maintaining safe conditions. It represents one of the most responsible and sensitive units of the entire railroad system. Signalmen are directly Involved with expanding the mileage of protected track, and modernizing existing railroad plants. Their activities necessitate smooth coordination with other units of the system to insure maximum safety and efficiency.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Doble's personal and professional files. It is largely composed of agreements and correspondence between union officials and local members and grievance chairmen, N.R.A.B. cases and other pertinent to railroading in general and to signalmen. Overall, the files reveal the process and function of the union hierarchy and general principles of union organization. The contents make evident certain achievements and benefits for the workers and the industry which have contributed to the fostering of harmonious Industrial relations.
The significant correspondence in this accession was generated by Doble, and by C.K. Fields (vice-president, legislative representative), J.M. Pattee (general chairman); W.E. Aurand (general secretary-treasurer), A.E. Lyon (grand president), D.W. Helt (grand president) Jesse Clark (president) and local officers of the Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen. Other correspondents include officers and employees of the Association of General Chairmen, New York Central; the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes; the Michigan Central Railroad; the New York Central Railroad; the Peoria and Eastern Railroad; and the Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad.
Files of the chairman of the New York Central Railroad (Lines West) of the Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen of America, including information regarding labor relations on the Michigan Central, Peoria and Eastern, and Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroads.
Materials on work jurisdiction (1931-1957) include correspondence (1933-1957) regarding workers other than signalmen performing signal work (i.e., electricians of the equipment department, section men, International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, maintenance of way shop employees, bridge and building department forces, Western Union Telegraph Company, communications department); seniority rights in both the transportation and signal department; and letters regarding carrier violations in the observance of craft lines as defined in the scope rules of the signalmen's agreement, and the contracting out of signal work.
Materials on the Legal Aid Department (1932) established for the purpose of advising injured members and dependents of those who died as the result of injuries regarding their legal rights and remedies under the Federal Employers' Liability Act; also include rules and regulations of the legal aid service of the Brotherhood.
Materials on color perception (1935-1945) include letters regarding an employee being disqualified for being unable to meet visual acuity standards, an employee removed from his position because of defective color perception, and demotion because of alleged color blindness.
Materials on political legislation (1946-1949) include a copy of HR.3020 to amend the National Labor Relations Act to provide additional facilities for the mediation of labor disputes affecting commerce, and to equalize legal responsibilities of labor organizations and employers; copy of HR.2536 to amend the Interstate Commerce Act (1946); endorsements by Railway Labor's Political League for the general election (1948); Congressional voting records (1946-1949); and Senate speeches on labor by Hubert H. Humphrey (1949).
Materials on the National Railroad Adjustment Board (1937-1950) include letters regarding international highway forwarders (1941) (trucks to be used in international service with all the bonding privileges accorded railroads); letters in opposition to a bill to construct and operate a belt conveyer between various points in Ohio; and letters regarding S.150/HR.628 reducing total freight revenues for railroads in the transport of coal and iron; minutes of a meeting called to organize a joint committee of railroad management and employees in Michigan for legislative purposes (1939) and minutes of the joint council of the Michigan railroad industry (1939); also a resolution outlining basic requirements of public policy bearing upon the relationship between competing forms of transportation.
Materials on the St. Lawrence Seaway Project (1941-1952) include press releases; letters regarding opposition of railroad labor to the St. Lawrence Seaway Project (1952); circulars from Tom J. McGrath (executive director, National St. Lawrence Project Conference, a nationwide organization in opposition to the St. Lawrence Seaway Project); and papers and publications on the proposed project and its effects.
Miscellaneous materials on railing protection, on signals, on strikes, and on reinstatements (1940-1958) include letters on signalmen positions abolished due to conditions arising from the locomotive firemen's strike, with a protest to the Railroad Retirement Board regarding the method of filing applications and allowing unemployment compensation during the strike; memorandum of understanding (1950) between the Brotherhood and the Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad, and the Lake Erie and Eastern Railroad in connection with restoration of small forces with revised operating rules upon the termination of the strike of conductors and trainmen on these properties; minutes (with by-laws) of the meeting of the Association of General Chairmen, Standard Labor Organizations on the New York Central System (1957); a paper supporting enactment of state legislation providing for the protection of employees adversely affected by the abandonment of railroad facilities; and letters regarding questions concerning work stoppages called by another craft or crafts.
Also included are transcripts of investigations to determine cause and responsibility for accidental damage to motor cars (1951); report of the proceedings of the General System Committee meetings of the New York Central lines; by-laws of the General Committee of the New York Central Railroad (Lines West) of the Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen (BRS) (1931); amalgamation of various lines of the New York Central system (1931); proposed by-laws and general rules of the General Grievance Committee of New York Central lines, BRS; minutes of meetings of New York Central lines (1927); reports of the secretary-treasurer, New York Central (Lines West) (1929-1960); financial statements of the General System Committee (1933-1952); minutes of meetings of the general chairman and BRS officers (1944-1960); conference (with by-laws) for the formation of a co-operative association of general chairmen representing the standard railroad labor organizations on the New York Central system lines (1932); circular letters (1952-1956) from the office of General Chairman Doble regarding protection of men working on highway crossings (1953); union shop operations (1956); recall of men laid off during the steel strike; leaves of absence (1955-1956); and reports of Doble (1934-1946).
Other matters include the question of whether Canadian employees working for the Michigan Central Railroad in Canada are subject to the provisions of railroad unemployment insurance (1938); settlement of work claims (1954-1955); letters regarding BRS conducting an organizing campaign among signal department employees on the New York Central system and its request to represent signal foremen and inspectors; files on organizing by the American Railway Supervisors' Association; minutes of general chairmen and local chairmen of the New York Central System (1929); and decisions of the 40-Hour Week Committee on revision of make-up time rules, traveling time, starting time, Sunday and holiday pay, day's work and overtime, reduction in force rules, stand-by rules, bulletin rules, and shift rules.
Materials on wages (1926-1956) include discussion of railroad organizations co-operating in opposing the national wage reduction movement inaugurated by the carriers.
Materials on veterans (1944-1949) include agreements and letters covering employees entering and leaving military service.
Materials on consolidation and absorptions (1932-1959) include a proposed rule governing adjustment of employee seniority affected by consolidation of seniority districts; letters regarding bidding rights, merger of and consolidation of seniority districts; a report, agreement, and letter regarding the protection of rights and interests of railway employees in any consolidation or unification of railroad facilities; seniority dispute between locals; seniority consolidation rule; displacement rights; and a membership drive by the American Railway Supervisors' Association of the New York Central system, conducted among signal inspectors and general foremen.
Materials on vacation include (1931-1953) letters on vacation with pay, plan for vacation, vacation for non-operating employees, vacation allowance to estate of deceased employee, vacation for those entering military service, vacation schedule, vacation to employees on 3-trick assignments (1940-1951), and vacation agreements with drafts and revisions (1931-1953).
Materials on overtime, Canadian District Public Relations, and consolidations (1930-1961) include letters regarding Canadian members coming into the United States and exercising seniority rights (1941); Council Order No. 8682 declaring six holidays per year for the duration of World War II (1942); Canadian selective service order regarding government employment of union members to further the war effort (1942); a strike of locomotive engineers, firemen and conductors on the New York Central system (Lines West), Michigan Central railroad, and the Big Four Railroads (1952); rights of promoted men when their positions are abolished (1952); and participation in the joint 1961 wage and rules movement for a general wage increase; numerous other routine matters regarding individual grievances, clauses in contracts and government regulations.
Materials on work claims and disputes (1951-1963) include grievances (1957-1963) regarding wages, seniority, working conditions, safety matters, craft jurisdiction, fringe benefits, overtime, promotion, discipline, dismissal, overtime, meal expense, and theft (company and personal) (1957-1965); minutes of BRS state legislative representatives (1956-1961); report on activities of state legislative representatives of BRS (1953-1955); a petition to Congress urging the repeal of the portion of the Railway Labor Act which permits negotiation of union shop agreements; letters regarding veterans' reemployment rights (1953-1963); claims by the United Railroad Operating Crafts that it is a national organization and entitled to participate in selection and designation of National Railroad Adjustment Board (NRAB) labor members (1958); application of union shop agreement to veterans and those on leave of absence; validity of union shop amendment and union shop agreement; also circular letters from Jesse Clark regarding federal legislation affecting railroad employees (1958-1960); and the Railroad Yardmasters of America organizing campaign within the New York Central system.
Materials on the union shop and the Travelers Insurance Company (1951-1963) include transcripts of hearings on union shop agreement violations (1952-1962), the health and welfare movement, and the wage movement of the Benefit Association of Railway Employees (1955), among related documents.
Additional materials (1936-1958) include letters regarding work week, equal distribution of employment, an official strike ballot regarding wage requests of 1942; Railway Labor Executives' Association resolution, statements, and reports dealing with employment of war prisoners on the railroads (1942); correspondence regarding the Pennsylvania-New York Central Railroad merger (1962); record books of BRS expenses (1937-1952); a memorandum relating to "certain" Chinese railway engineers training for railroad service (1944); and New York Central lines regulations and requirements governing employee physical examinations and re-examinations upon promotion (1933-1948); apprenticeship training in the signal department (1947-1956); regulations governing the issuance of free or reduced rate transportation (1942); a record book (1936) of BRS Grand Lodge dues for various locals (1936); and minutes and proceedings of the 1958 BRS convention.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5182 P: Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen of America Photographs
Color blindness -- United States; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; Liability for railroad accidents -- United States; Prisoners of war -- United States; Railroads -- United States -- Abandonment; Railroads -- United States -- Consolidation; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Railroads -- Employees; Railroad signalmen; Collective labor agreements -- Railroads -- United States; Contracting out -- Railroads -- United States; Grievance procedures -- Railroads -- New York (State); Hours of labor -- Railroads -- United States; Life insurance -- United States; Unemployment insurance -- Canada; Job security -- Railroads -- United States; Labor discipline -- Railroads -- United States; Labor disputes -- Railroads -- United States; Labor-management cooperation -- Michigan; Locomotive engineers, Chinese -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Misconduct -- Railroads -- United States; Open and closed shop -- Railroads -- United States; Railroad employees -- United States -- Medical Examinations; Railroads -- Military aspects -- United States; Railroads -- Safety measures -- United States; Retirement -- Railroads -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Railroads -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States -- Jurisdictional disputes; Railroads -- Labor unions -- United States; Vacations, Employee -- Railroads -- United States; Veterans' benefits -- United States; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Work assignment -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Canada; Work rules -- Railroads -- United States; Working conditions -- Railroads -- United States; Employee rules; Doble, William J., 1904-1972.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978; Benefit Association Railway Employees; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; Lake Erie and Eastern Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad; New York Central Railroad; Peoria and Eastern Railroad; Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad Company; Railway Labor's Political League; St. Lawrence Seaway Development Corporation; United States. National Railroad Adjustment Board
3834064
- Elkhart Signal Shop Work, 1931-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Painting of Signal Apparatus, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cincinnati Northern RR, 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Installation of Relay Houses - N.Y. Central, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Shipley vs. Pittsburgh and Lake Erie RR Company, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Maume River Bridge, Toledo, Ohio, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- C.R. Interlocking Plant, Chicago, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Western Union, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Shop Crafts Agreement, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- National Mediation Board - Representation of Employees, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Scope and Contents
  NY Central RR
- Order of Railroad Telegraphers, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Local 35, Doughton, Ohio, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Adjustment of Pay - Michigan Central, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- ORT, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- ORT, Monroe, Michigan, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Michigan Central Railroad, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Machinist, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- M of W, Illinois, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Pay Adjustment P&E Railroad, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- San Francisco Trades Council vs. General Railway Signal Company, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- ORT, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Senate Bill 74, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Roster of Senate and House of Representatives
- Local 35 - Maintenance, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- C.N.R.R., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Sheet Metal Workers, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- National Railroad Adjustment Board, 3rd Division, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  pamphlets
- Commuications Department, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Grand Lodge Agreement, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- M of W and Indiana Harbor Belt Railroad Company, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- N.R.A.B., 3rd Division - Reading Company, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- N.R.A.B. - M of W - Delaware and Hudson Railroad Corporation, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  M of W agreements
- N.Y. Central Lines West - B.R.S. of A, agreement, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Train banners
- M.C.R.R., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- I.B.E.W., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- I.B.E.W., 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- N.R.A.B., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Chicago, Rock Island & Pacific Company
- Local 41, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Rules 140 and 141 for Electrical Workers, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Local 10, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Scope of Work, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- O.R.T., 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Crossing Gates - Repairs, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- N.Y.C. System - I.B.E.W., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- N.Y.C. System - I.B.E.W., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- I.B.E.W. Work Rules, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- B.R.S. of A. Michigan, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Jesse Clark, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Employers Liability Act, 1932-1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Legal Aid Service (Box 1, Folder 49)
- L. Hix on disqualification due to color test failure, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Vision regulations, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Demotion of D. Hunsinger Due to poor color perception, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Demotion of Kubsh - Defective color perception, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- P & LE Ortho-Rater, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Copy article on color vision, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Missing (Box 1, Folder 56)
- "Rule 12" - Interpretation, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Claims by workers for overtime pay, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Anti-Labor Bills, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  LMRA
- Legislative Report - U.S. Department of Labor, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- H.R. 2536, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Railway Labor's Political League, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- UN - Dumbarton Oaks (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Speech - National Labor Policy, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- NRAB - Awards, Third Division (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Awards, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Agreement - Canadian Representative of U.S. NRAB, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Michigan Legislation on Trucking Activities, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Coordinated Shipments, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Beit Conveyor, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- U.S. Mail, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Public Policy - Competing Forms of Transportation (Box 1, Folder 72)
- St. Lawrence Seaway, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Colorlight Signal Poles, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Bracket Poles, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Floodlight Poles, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Strike Payments, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  Michigan Central Railroad
- Pittsburgh, Lake Erie/Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad Co. Strike, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Layoffs - Indian Harbor Belt, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Operating rules, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- Local Chairmen, Western System Lines, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Signal Force, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 82)
- Interlocking joints, 1949-1956 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  Diagrams
- Chicago & Western Indiana Railroad Co. /State Line Interlocker, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Walnut St. Nickel Plate Railroad, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Ridgeway, Ohio, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 86)
- Crestline Plant, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Cincinnati & Ohio/Delaware Interlocking, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 88)
- Calumet Park, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 89)
- Oakland City, Indiana, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 90)
- Fostoria, Ohio, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 91)
- Union Switch & Signal Com. /Huff Interlocking, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Nickel Plate Railroad/St. Mary's Interlocking, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 93)
- Signal Apparatus/Inspection of Foreign Lines, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 94)
- Grand Trunk West/Milawaukee Junction Interlocking, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 95)
- Wayne Interlocking Plant, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 96)
- Columbus Union Depot, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 97)
- Granite City, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 98)
- Warren, Pa. Automatic Gates, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 99)
- G.M.&O. /Alton, Illinois, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 100)
- Greenville, Ohio /Baltimore & Ohio Railroad, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  Inoperative Distant Signals
- Miami Crossing, Ohio, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  Cab Signals
- Preston Interlocking/Terre Haute, Indiana, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 103)
- Wapakoneta, Ohio/Baltimore & Ohio, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 104)
- Big Four/Jackson Street, Danville Illinois, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 105)
- Target Singal at Slater, Ohio/D.T.&I., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 106)
- Pelton Interlocking/Ontario, Canada, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 107)
- Ames Interlocking/Crawfordsville, Indiana, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 108)
- Franklin, Pa., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 109)
- Bridge over Cuyahoga River, Cleveland, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  Diagrams; agreements
- Streator, Illinois, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  Flashing H. Signals/Crossing Belts
- Toledo Terminal Railroad Tracks - Vulcan, Ohio, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 112)
- East Alton and Bridge Junction, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 113)